<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"> <channel> <title>Darshan Soni</title> <description>Integrated Engineering student interested in transportation systems. Hobbyist front end web developer. Enthusiast of all things Design. </description> <link>http://darshandsoni.com//</link> <atom:link href="http://darshandsoni.com//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/> <pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2016 18:33:29 -0800</pubDate> <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2016 18:33:29 -0800</lastBuildDate> <generator>Jekyll v3.0.1</generator> <item> <title>Optimising static sites</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;Static sites, are generally speaking, much faster than dynamic ones abound with javascript and server requests from the very start. This is because they are precompiled and served to users as they are on the web (excluding any special requests e.g. google map embeds). Hosting on a cloud based platform such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/s3/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Amazon S3&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalocean.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt; also drastically improves speed since the content is hardly ever down and retrieved from the best possible geographic location.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;That said, static sites can get slightly bloated over time and a perfect place to test out loading time is Google’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/speed/pagespeed/insights/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pagespeed insights&lt;/a&gt; which gives your site a test run, returns a scorecard and also gives suggestions on how to make your response time faster.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One thing you’ll notice it telling you is to use inline CSS or js instead of an external file reference to cull the additional request made for that file. Of course this only applies to small files, but practically speaking, not every js file can be inlined. Chances are you will be using some external reference for plugins or even bootstrap itself. A quick trick to reduce bloat here is to minify your site’s existing js, html and css files.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Worry not, for you do not have to do this manually. There is a jekyll plugin for this! And now you’re going to say, “But… GitHub pages won’t run those due to –safe mode etc…” and again, worry not! The plugin minifies your html, css, javascript and xmls as you build your site, so when it is pushed up to GitHub it is already compiled and does not call out any custom liquid tags like the flickr or 500px ones. To enact all this, simply run:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; gem install jekyll-minifier &lt;/code&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Then to your _config.yml file add the following:&lt;br /&gt; &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt; gems: - jekyll-minifier &lt;/code&gt; &lt;br /&gt; And that’s it! Try run the pagespeed insights again (note that it has a cache time of 30s) and see the improvements! For more information, check out the Git page for &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/digitalsparky/jekyll-minifier&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;jekyll-minifier&lt;/a&gt; thanks to digitalsparky.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate> <link>http://darshandsoni.com//jekyll/2016/02/07/Optimising-static-sites.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://darshandsoni.com//jekyll/2016/02/07/Optimising-static-sites.html</guid> <category>Jekyll</category> </item> <item> <title>Adding images to Jekyll&#39;s post feed - without plugins</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/merlos/jekyll-auto-image&quot;&gt;jekyll-auto-image&lt;/a&gt; plugin is a pretty useful tool to get thumbnail images to display on a blog main page. However, this plugin is not yet supported by GitHub pages and will display broken image links if used with GitHub pages. In general, I prefer the minimalistic approach of using powerful liquid tags and plain old html to get the job done.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;This method assumes you are already implementing the &lt;a href=&quot;http://getbootstrap.com&quot;&gt;Bootstrap framework&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;adding-a-thumbnail-to-a-post&quot;&gt;1. Adding a thumbnail to a post&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Choose a thumbnail image, add it to an images folder in your root (e.g. /images/ or /assets/). Alternatively find a permanent url for an image you want to use.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-markdown&quot; data-lang=&quot;markdown&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;---&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;layout&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;post&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;goes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;here&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;categories&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;jekyll&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;thumbnail&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;pi&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;/images/customthumbnail.jpg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;---&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;adding-a-default-thumbnail&quot;&gt;2. Adding a default thumbnail&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sometimes, you may not have an appropriate thumbnail image for a particular post. In this case, we want jekyll to just use a default thumbnail saved in your images foler. Put a file in there named nothumbnail.jpg or similar.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h3 id=&quot;adding-liquid-tags-to-render-thumbnails&quot;&gt;3. Adding Liquid tags to render thumbnails&lt;/h3&gt; &lt;p&gt;Here’s where the magic happens. We need the post directory to render the thumbnail image. In case there isn’t one, it should render the default thumbnail. On your blog’s directory page (e.g. blog.md), add the following liquid tag loops to do &lt;a href=&quot;https://truongtx.me/2013/01/05/thumbnail-post-list-for-jekyll-bootstrap/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate> <link>http://darshandsoni.com//jekyll/2016/02/02/adding-images-to-jekyll-post-feed.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://darshandsoni.com//jekyll/2016/02/02/adding-images-to-jekyll-post-feed.html</guid> <category>Jekyll</category> </item> <item> <title>Reasons why TransLink is a complete failure</title> <description>&lt;div class=&quot;alert alert-danger alert-dismissible&quot; role=&quot;alert&quot;&gt; &lt;button type=&quot;button&quot; class=&quot;close&quot; data-dismiss=&quot;alert&quot; aria-label=&quot;Close&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&amp;times;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/button&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Content coming soon:&lt;/strong&gt; This is a research post in progress. Check back soon for updates! &lt;/div&gt; &lt;!-- #### 1. The New Flyer fleet TransLink uses a fleet consisting of almost only [New Flyer and Nova buses](http://www.translink.ca/-/media/Documents/plans_and_projects/expansion_upgrades/Fleet%20Pictorial.pdf){:target=&quot;_blank&quot;}; buses with hugely inferior quality when compared to European manufacturers such as Volvo. This one is a more prickly issue than poorly trained drivers: Both companies have manufacturing in Canada and we bring in the whole issue of sourcing locally and using a proudly Canadian fleet. #### 2. Drivers &gt;I&#39;m normally quite hesitant to critique a large group of hardworking individuals such as bus drivers. However, my critique of them here is not so much at them individually rather, how TransLink operates with them. When I first came to BC in 2012, one thing that struck me was the politeness of the drivers on board buses. Of course, there is the occasional grumpy driver, but overall the drivers I came across were courteous, sympathetic and caring. Welcome greetings were commonplace, the lack of correct fare was not met with the same scorn as in Paris or London and drivers were willing to get up and assist passengers. I suspect this stems from the broader culture of kindness and general decency prevalent in much of rural BC and embedded itself in the days when BC Transit still operated in Vancouver. Here are the issues I have with drivers: Firstly, a large number of them go a step beyond common decency and happily engage in conversation with nearby passengers / supervisors. This is both *dangerous* and *irresponsible* on their part. What follows is that stops may sometimes be skipped, driving becomes erratic and customers waiting at &quot;quiet&quot; bus stops may be ignored. As a customer, I would much rather have a timely, reliable and safe experience than a polite driver. It&#39;s not a lack of appreciation of their jovial nature, it&#39;s a prioritising of safety above all else. The second issue with them is largely down to the way TransLink allocates their routes. Unlike many other cities, Vancouver bus drivers get shuffled on their routes much more often. I suppose that this might be so as not to bore them, but the result is bus drivers who are not completely comfortable with their assigned route. A common sight is the west-bound 041 approaching UBC - some drivers inadvertently miss the turnng onto Wesbrook Mall, to the ire of everyone getting off at TRIUMF Centre or everyone waiting in Wesbrook Village. The third and probably most important issue is their training with large vehicles. It hurts me to say that I consider Vancouver bus drivers to be amongst the worst when it comes to spatial awareness and ride comfort control. Anyone commuting may testify to a real bone-shaking ride if they&#39;re standing. Yes, the problem is also down to the bus manufacturers using inferior suspension systems, and TransLink&#39;s arbitrary &quot;2 block stop distance&quot; (something discussed separately here), but there are countless incidents where I have seen a driver accelerate rapidly away from a stop, ignoring the impending red light ahead and then slamming the breaks to stop at the intersection. I mean **why? Seriously! Why?** And let&#39;s not forget the nauseating tapping of the accelerator and brake pedals when waiting for the light to turn green... &quot;Just wait for the bloody light to turn green&quot;. It&#39;s one of those things that is barely felt in a small car but amplified disturbingly on a large vehicle such as a bus. #### 3. Switching to dynamic scheduling #### 9. Incompatible inter-service changes #### 4. The U-Pass (tap card) fiasco #### 5. Stupidly designed fare gates #### 6. Different branding within the same system #### 8. Poor demarcation #### 7. Evenly spaced stops (arbirarily) #### 10. Lack of redundancy #### 11. Low goals &gt; Now, showing off about being North America&#39;s Best transit system is like boasting about being the best student in the bottom 4 of a class of 30 students - it&#39;s meaningless and nobody cares. --&gt; </description> <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate> <link>http://darshandsoni.com//transportation/2016/02/01/Reasons-TransLink-is-a-complete-failure.html</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">http://darshandsoni.com//transportation/2016/02/01/Reasons-TransLink-is-a-complete-failure.html</guid> <category>Transportation</category> </item> </channel> </rss>