<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://darshandsoni.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://darshandsoni.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-07-26T22:08:24-07:00</updated><id>https://darshandsoni.com/</id><title type="html">Darshan Soni</title><subtitle>Personal site and blog for Darshan Soni, Integrated Engineer.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">From Ubuntu to Fedora to Solus</title><link href="https://darshandsoni.com/2017/05/02/migrating-to-solus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Ubuntu to Fedora to Solus" /><published>2017-05-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://darshandsoni.com/2017/05/02/migrating-to-solus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://darshandsoni.com/2017/05/02/migrating-to-solus.html">&lt;p&gt;This article is a reasonably long one, but it summarises my linux experiences so far and details the reasons I for me to adopt Solus as my daily driver. I’m not in a position to technically assess the developers of linux based distributions and give them all credit for their hard work as Open-Source project developers. Instead, take this as one account from a run-of-the-mill engineering student who just needs a pleasant daily driver :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-leaving-ubuntu&quot;&gt;1. Leaving Ubuntu&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/b4/Ubuntu_Desktop_12.10.png/1024px-Ubuntu_Desktop_12.10.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Ubuntu Desktop&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I adopted &lt;a href=&quot;https://getfedora.com&quot;&gt;Fedora&lt;/a&gt; 2 years ago, as my first “distrojump” after a 6 year long Ubuntu stint. Ubuntu was my first ever linux OS and installing it flipped my computing world upside down. Nothing can replace the years of learning I had on my good old Hardy Heron, arguably Ubuntu’s most famous release to date. My reasons for jumping to Fedora were multiple and examined in depth below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-desktop-environment&quot;&gt;The desktop environment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest of these was probably Ubuntu’s complete rebranding and shift to the Unity desktop environment. Although Unity became fairly stable and well received by users late in its life cycle, there’s no denying that when it was first introduced, it was incomplete and a big shock to GNOME 2.0 users. I have a theory that Unity was continually hated upon, even after it became a polished desktop environment, simply because there remained an entire strata of users who began their Ubuntu experience with GNOME 2.0 and had the rug pulled from under their feet. So while there were new users to Ubuntu post-2012 who saw and grew to love a very polished Unity environment, behind them was a generation of disgruntled GNOME 2.0 users. It didn’t get much better for the GNOME camp either because GNOME itself rebranded in its 3.0 release, making for a UX disaster that upset Linus Torvalds himself. That left a huge crowd of users flocking to other Desktop Environments to call home, myself included. Because of my busy schedule, I settled with Unity for a while. In the next few years, I frequently shuffled between Unity and GNOME 3, seeing improvements in them, but never quite feeling satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-ppa-system&quot;&gt;The PPA system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu, with its Debian base was like home to me. My world never grew beyond &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;apt-get&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;add-apt-repository&lt;/code&gt;. For one, GNOME 3 was trying to fix a lot of issues, but the frozen state of Ubuntu’s repositories made it impossible to get cutting edge releases of GNOME without adding other PPAs. And that’s all fine, until I began to add PPAs all over the place, just to test new sotftware. This became tedious hell when I made system upgrades every 6 months and found tonnes of repositories, conflicting packages, broken links, unmet dependencies… the list goes on. I basically broke Ubuntu so much that I had to nuke and pave. And this happened over and over again. It was becoming very evident that given my interests in getting updates quicker, I needed to switch to something else. It’s not that Ubuntu was bad in this sense; rather, I now had different purposes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;boredom&quot;&gt;Boredom?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I felt I was on a plateau with my Ubuntu knowledge. I needed a change in working environment; something with finer grain control and a new routine! This isn’t to say there was nothing else to learn on an Ubuntu machine - far from it really! It was just one of those situations where a change was needed and one that didn’t involve peppering my machine with developer PPAs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there you go, enough weight behind the push factors to lead me away from Ubuntu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-my-fedora-era&quot;&gt;2. My Fedora Era&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fedora really appealed to me. It was known to be bleeding-edge, yet remarkably solid, in part thanks to the work of Red Hat in supporting it. I got my introduction to the rpm world and got my hands dirty with the dnf package manager (The yum package manager had just been deprecated when I flashed Fedora on). Loved it. For me, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DNF&lt;/code&gt; just handled things so much better than &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;apt-get&lt;/code&gt;. I didn’t get as technical with it, but it seemed rock solid with the visible transaction checks and a richer list of package versions. I got to experience bleeding-edge GNOME 3 and was excited about having software way before &lt;a href=&quot;https://omgubuntu.co.uk&quot;&gt;omgubuntu&lt;/a&gt; could spread the word to it’s ‘buntu crowd - tongue heavily pressed to my cheek there! It was all fine over the 2 years of use but eventually its fair share of problems also came by. Mind you, I still have a lot of affection for the Fedora project. It has by far been one of the most reliable systems I’ve ever used and RedHat is without a doubt a remarkable example of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SaaS&quot;&gt;SaaS&lt;/a&gt; done right. Their documentation is very human-readable and the software base is rock-soid, which is to be expected given their reliability clientele. The fedora forums were a very helpful space: very little “noob shaming”; prompt replies and concise threads thanks to the userbase being, on average, more experienced than the wide variety of Ubuntu users. I don’t have a metric for that last statement… just a feeling I had.
So anyway, what could possibly drive me away from Fedy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kde-multiscreen-woes&quot;&gt;KDE Multiscreen woes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My frustration with the direction of the GNOME project kept growing. It seemed to me that they were constantly driving towards a “dumbing down” of their interface: taking away power user elements from Nautilus, the default file manager; hardly introducing an ecosystem of useful extensions; becoming very resource heavy and bizarrely driving away from the desktop experience to a half baked tabled interface that had no practically viable hardware to match it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these issues frustrated me and had me looking for another desktop environment. One of my colleagues pointed me towards KDE, being a longtime fan of it. I had some reservations about it, and to know why, you have to go way back in the day. Long before stable, beautiful Plasma 5 that we know today, to the frustrating years of KDE 4. In transitioning from KDE 3 to 4, they basically pulled a “GNOME 3.0”. A bug-ridden interface that alienated users. My only experience with it was a live Kubuntu iso that played up massively with my ageing Acer box and I never looked back at it. So I figured, ok, I’ll give KDE another chance then! I just transitioned to a new job so it was the perfect time of quiet to try something new. Oh creamy hummus, how I love what I saw! It was so pleasant on the eyes and the interface was far more intuitive than GNOME. The Qt framework was really made it a coherent space. Then, I discovered the level of fine grain control I had over all my settings. I’m talking kioslaves, krunner, drop-down terminals and all the other hidden goodies.
Then you have tools like KDE connect that were so simple, but did their job so well. The Unix philosophy taken seriously I tell you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it all came crashing down with multiscreen woes and package bloat. Now, these aren’t core KDE problems and I do sympathise with KDE devs on this. They’ve frequently talked about why multiscreen is a complicated thing to maintain and it certainly makes it trickier in that KDE is used on so many platforms that there’s a blurred line between distribution level bugs and global desktop environment bugs. A multiple monitor bug with the KDisplayManager popped up during one of my busiest times, rendering any secondary display completely useless. I won’t go into the technical details of the bug, but essentially, my screen was half blank at all times. Rolling back didn’t work as it would re-update when I pulled in any other packages that depended on it. And uninstalling it worked, but rendered my secondary display useless. With no time to deal with it and a big backlog on the developers’ ends, I kicked it off and looked for something quick and easy to get going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-i-got-myself-xfce&quot;&gt;So I got myself Xfce&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello Xfce. Why Xfce? It’s old-school gtk2. Barebones but modular. It was my GNOME 2.0 (MATE was still experimental in my mind then). Xfce kept me going for a few months. It was minimal, extremely stable and modular. I was even more familiar with it because I swapped crouton on my commute-friendly Chromebook for a fully-fledged single linux distribution, &lt;a href=&quot;https://galliumos.org/&quot;&gt;GalliumOs&lt;/a&gt;, which is a Chromebook adapted Xfce-based distro that runs like butter on low-end hardware. Xfce to this day, remains something of a “homely” environment for me. Give it to me anywhere and I’m fine with it. Sure, the stock version of it can be ugly but most of my desktop work is heavily keyboard based anyway. But Xfce is an aging DE. It still uses gtk2 - even MATE is moving to gtk3 now! It’s also known for having spells of no updates at all, with hardly any adaptation to changing multimedia content and user interaction styles. So I was ready for a new environment!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;too-much-bleeding-edge&quot;&gt;Too much bleeding-edge?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look, Fedora is through and through, a bleeding-edge distribution. I get access to the latest packages, but I have to accept breakages when they’re untested. The project doesn’t hide this reality and truth be told, it is remarkably stable for a bleeding edge distribution! Again, it’s probably a matter of my needs not being met instead of an issue with Fedora itself (apart from that little KDE display settings debacle). After giving it some thought, I realised that Fedora would be fine on a dev machine where I’d test stuff continuously. It seems that over the past few years, my Toshiba laptop has become a bit of a “base” for me: Sturdy enough to handle my engineering projects, but also holding its own as my home entertainment system. All I do at home is connect it to a nicer display. So I needed something more stable for a home computer. Perhaps I overcompensated for the out-of-date Ubuntu software with a zealous Fedora machine that chugged down updates sometimes more frequently than daily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I needed was a “curated, bleeding edge machine perfectly cut out for home computing use”. If any Solus core dev read that statement, I suspect they’ll be tingling with excitement! I’d love to have new software on my machine, but I don’t need AUR level depth; most packages are redundant anyway, there’s tens of wrappers for every core package I’ve seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-adopting-solus&quot;&gt;3. Adopting Solus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been following developments at Solus ever since their relaunch from EvolveOS. What I saw really excited me. The close-knit team of developers got open-source projects and clearly communicated why Solus is being worked on and exactly who it’s for. It’s not just another “distro” based off of something else that ends up just containing a kernal, preferred desktop environment by a main developer and a menu of options that comes preconfigured for ease of use. No, far from it! Solus instead looks back at all the other operating systems and critically asks: What did not work? What can be made better? What should be rewritten? Where can we eliminate redundancies from older systems? And these questions need answering if you’re going to take modern operating systems to a whole new level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; src=&quot;/images/solus.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;budgie-desktop-as-an-example&quot;&gt;Budgie desktop as an example&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good example of this “learn-from-old-mistakes” approach is with the flagship desktop environment, Budgie. I’ll be honest, when I first saw Budgie, it didn’t appeal to me. I groaned at the prospect of parsing through the pros and cons of &lt;em&gt;yet another desktop environment&lt;/em&gt;. But once I tried Solus out and then read into the development of Budgie, a lightbulb went off. Budgie was created for a specific purpose: A home computing environment (think desktop, home laptop connected to peripherals etc). Why aim to develop something for every use case and handle it badly? Why create an interface that displays beautifully on a tablet device that doesn’t exist, with the market clearly indicating it is not interested in it, while sacrificing a good experience on a small but guaranteed chunk of the market that demands a good desktop environment? Budgie was written to specifically address this use case. It doesn’t imagine that it could appear on a tablet somewhere. Nor a phone. Nor a server. It does one job and does it brilliantly. Budgie was written with gtk components as a base, but because its new, it didn’t need to import legacy cruft that the GNOME platform itself currently has. Or implement dated solutions like compiz when it doesn’t need that lag. Ikey Doherty, the project lead for Solus has talked in great depth about his experiences working with the GNOME shell and GTK in some &lt;a href=&quot;https://latenightlinux.com/late-night-linux-episode-08/&quot;&gt;podcasts&lt;/a&gt;. Realising that at some point, Budgie was not getting what it needed from GTK and the frustrations / limitations of working around it, the Budgie team made a decision to rewrite it all in Qt. Sure, it’s a lot of sweat and tears, but if you know what you want, why compromise with hacky solutions? Qt in their eyes presents a well-supported framework with a very helpful forum of developers and a homogeneous interface that allows applications to feel native. I really admire this work ethic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;packaging&quot;&gt;Packaging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solus also offers cutting-edge packages but has two huge advantages over other operating systems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Carefully curated cutting edge packages ensure that I still get the latest of what's out there, but a quality assurance that they work and can support a stable system.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt; Packages are built specifically for Solus with a preference to use native dependencies. This makes a huge difference for install times because you're not getting a package that goes and looks for a dependency from another distribution written in another language that also requires additional compile time.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have never seen a system that installs software as fast as Solus. In fact, the limiting factor has only been downloading the updates because North American users would receive it from Ireland. This is a problem Doherty seems to recognise all too well and after all, what do we expect from an independent OS that is funded by pure goodness of heart? To even have the download speeds we see right now is a privilege. Not one to accept defeat though, Solus now has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patreon.com/solus&quot;&gt;Patreon page&lt;/a&gt; which helps keeps the lights and cooling fans on. In due time, I’m sure we’ll get some nice global image distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a nervous feeling about packages when I first tested Solus on some spare hardware. There’s no AUR, Ubuntu PPAs or Fedora repositories. Does that mean I miss out on a tonne of software? To alleviate my concerns, I had to do some in-depth studying. By that, I mean listening to 6 hours of podcasts with Ikey, Joshua’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oMMfc8XxZhc&amp;amp;t=495s&quot;&gt;packaging&lt;/a&gt; guides and a dash of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLhhMWYdkJJbO2yxp4kkAE71KUZWpE3Por&quot;&gt;“Sundays with Solus”&lt;/a&gt; videos.
Then, one fine Spring day, I &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DarshanDSoni/status/855836908353486850&quot;&gt;nuke-and-paved&lt;/a&gt; it on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solus seems to have every package I’ve needed so far; the community is highly responsive to &lt;a href=&quot;https://solus-project.com/articles/packaging/request-a-package/en/&quot;&gt;package requests&lt;/a&gt; for missing necessities; building packages seems far easier and crucially, better documented than many other OSs. So, away goes my concern over packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; src=&quot;/images/eopkg.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;solus-works-like-a-charm&quot;&gt;Solus works like a charm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I have to say it’s refreshing to use Solus. I’m recording 3 second boot-up and shutdown times on a 5 year old, mid-range Toshiba laptop. I have some cutting edge software coming through pipes with a reassurance that they are reasonably well tested (at least on the stable repository), which is such a comfort on a “personal device” that I just need to be ready to go at all times. My development workflow has been a charm with all the usual tools like Atom, Rsync and rubygems ready to go. My home entertainment works out of the box - it seems to remember my settings as soon as I connect my external display with no need for tedious settings. I am very curious about the entertainment server, Plex, having never used it before, so more on that experiment soon! To the wonderful folks working hard on Solus right now, I tip my fedora to you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
a{
  text-decoration:underline;
}
&lt;/style&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This article is a reasonably long one, but it summarises my linux experiences so far and details the reasons I for me to adopt Solus as my daily driver. I’m not in a position to technically assess the developers of linux based distributions and give them all credit for their hard work as Open-Source project developers. Instead, take this as one account from a run-of-the-mill engineering student who just needs a pleasant daily driver :)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The AU Passport: A waste of time</title><link href="https://darshandsoni.com/2016/09/04/au-passport.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The AU Passport: A waste of time" /><published>2016-09-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-09-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://darshandsoni.com/2016/09/04/au-passport</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://darshandsoni.com/2016/09/04/au-passport.html">&lt;p&gt;People across the African continent have been chatting excitedly about the latest Pan-African creation: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.au.int/en/pressreleases/31182/african-union-passport-launched-during-opening-27th-au-summit-kigali&quot;&gt;The AU Passport&lt;/a&gt;. This new document is a direct draw from the European Union in that it serves as a travel document for all citizens of African Union member nations (basically the whole continent, excluding Morocco)* to travel the continent visa free.
The premise is great. As a Kenyan citizen, I’m extremely aware of how much of a hassle international travel is, based on my passport. Lengthy visa applications, outrageous processing and admin fees, tiresome prior planning and airport security harassment are just a few of the major hiccups. It’s certainly true that in this day and age, African travellers are still considered inferior and more of a liability than those from developed countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the inspiration for the AU passport — Europe’s borderless &lt;a href=&quot;http://ec.europa.eu/dgs/home-affairs/what-we-do/policies/borders-and-visas/index_en.htm&quot;&gt;Schengen area&lt;/a&gt; — has been a strong case for a single market. Yes, it’s not been a perfect ride; the past 2 years have painted a nasty picture with the migrant crisis, unfettered access for radical attackers, huge bailouts and sluggish economic growth. But the overarching fact is that despite all of this, the Schengen area is a huge success. One cannot deny the huge boost in growth, rapid development in the Eastern bloc and the immense travel culture change that came with it. Most Europeans take for granted the fact that they can just decide to pick up their belongings, choose a mode of transport and just settle in another country and make a living there with no paperwork at all. I digress though, the details of this are for another article.
So back to the new kid on the block: The AU Passport. Given it’s positive premise, why am I so negative about it? Here are my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;top-down-here-we-go-again&quot;&gt;Top down. Here we go again.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to any development on the continent, critics have been screaming this phrase for the last 30 years. Top down development continues to plague so many African innovations that people are tired of pointing it out. In this case, the AU passport was rolled out in full glam at the AU summit in July 2016. The first 2 passports were presented to Chadian president and AU chair Idriss Deby, and Rwandan president Paul Kagame respectively. Other heads of state will soon receive theirs, but that’s exactly the problem. Diplomats on the continent don’t actually have any issue with travel. Their possession of the passport is merely symbolic. Instead, a rollout should be done with ordinary people who would actually use one, have issues with it, give feedback and ultimately contribute towards the program by mutual investment. The users would gain from getting visa free access, the program would gain from getting increased travel and investment across borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Who gets the passport will depend on each government. They can decide to give it to, you know, good business people that they think can invest all across the continent and so forth. But the ultimate goal, as I said, is really to make sure that everybody moves freely.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;tbody&gt;
          &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;Fatima Haram Acyl&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;AU trade and industry commissioner&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;/tbody&gt;
      &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That statement in itself presents the problem in implementation. It hints that countries will have ultimate say over who gets it which beats the purpose of using this as a tool to elevate the travelling rights of all Africans. If oppressive regimes continue to flout rules on travel with the AU passport just as they do with current national passports, what’s the point? Moreover, the fact that “good business people” will get it first means we’re back to “money = more access”. And again, that is missing the point entirely. Business empire owners across the continent are already frequent travellers and have the resources to get visas quickly, operate multilaterally and use connections to get things done. The people who can’t travel are those in small, budding enterprises who are overwhelmed by cost and paperwork to spread their business over borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to accessibility based schemes such as AU passports, internet access or low bracket finance, successful initiatives such as M-Pesa, have started out with the common tier, not the high tier. If M-Pesa was first rolled out to NSE listed firms, nobody would have used it because big businesses were familiar with the banking sector and saw no need to change. Instead, they allowed the farmer in Kabarnet to send money to his nephew’s new enterprise in Mathare. Those are the people that needed and still need such a service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;no-universal-framework&quot;&gt;No universal framework&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst all the chatter about the new passports, one crucial piece is missing: a formal framework adhered to by all member nations. The AU admits that this still has to be drawn up but has not offered any specifics of when and how. The AU also say that each country will be responsible for the implementation of their own AU passports. With such sharp differences in laws across the continent, how can such a program ever succeed? For example, Mauritius, having a highly developed passport control agency may deny someone an AU passport if they pose a credible threat. Theoretically, that seeker could get the very same document in Somalia, where issuing offices might have far less control. Whilst a centralised processing office for the whole continent would be sluggish and ineffective, giving each of the 54 members control in their own way is an even bigger mess with corruption and loopholes rife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;integration&quot;&gt;Integration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a massive topic on it’s own. For arguments sake, let’s simplistically hypothesise that every AU member state was at a similar economic level (which by the way is crucial for an economic bloc of this size), there are still so many cultural, legal and political differences between so many nations that trusting a single passport control policy is a wildly unrealistic idea. The EU itself has strict and well defined conditions for new members but they also benefited from the fact that all the founding members were economically advanced countries already. And even this was put into question from the accession of Greece onwards, with critics crying foul about countries doctoring their economic figures just to get an entry into the EU.
Let’s look at Kenya and Tanzania — two friendly neighbours who share so much culturally. These two still cannot agree on a unified, borderless East African Community region. How can an AU-wide union even stand a chance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-realistic-alternative&quot;&gt;A realistic alternative&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of pursuing lofty, impractical goals of a posh, green leather booklet for Africans, work should be done on the actual policies between neighbour states. We have spent decades building institutions like ECOWAS, EAC, COMESA and the SADC. ECOWAS perhaps being the most successful when it comes to freedom of travel of member nation citizens. Why not invest more time and effort into formalizing these frameworks and then looking at further integrations as necessary? Having focussed development on a few blocs comprised of a select few members is likely to go a longer way than a rough plan to make 50- some nations agree to a common framework.
The problem with labour mobility in Africa is not that big businesses can’t spread across the continent, it’s that budding enterprises can’t do it thanks to the cost and time hurdles of getting paperwork done. Any proposed solution to this should target a lay person with their ordinary national ID document and not tycoons who can afford to pay their way through the system anyway.
Integration of all sorts is also a huge issue and focussing on smaller blocs allows countries to develop faster together. Think of it this way, say that effort went into the existing 5 members of the EAC: Kenya, Uganda, Tanzania, Rwanda and Burundi. Given ample time, the economies would align much closer to each other thanks to common goals, mutual interests in infrastructure such as ports and common laws already in existence. The AU would then have only 4-5 sub-blocs of nations that require further alignment. But by this time, people would have already begun to enjoy the benefit of free travel, at least regionally of not continentally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s sad to see such a wasteful, ill-prepared solution being applied to a big African problem in the form of the AU passport. It would be lovely to see AU member governments rethink their proposed solution on this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;*Edit: Correct at the time of writing. Morocco has since re-joined the AU.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">People across the African continent have been chatting excitedly about the latest Pan-African creation: The AU Passport. This new document is a direct draw from the European Union in that it serves as a travel document for all citizens of African Union member nations (basically the whole continent, excluding Morocco)* to travel the continent visa free. The premise is great. As a Kenyan citizen, I’m extremely aware of how much of a hassle international travel is, based on my passport. Lengthy visa applications, outrageous processing and admin fees, tiresome prior planning and airport security harassment are just a few of the major hiccups. It’s certainly true that in this day and age, African travellers are still considered inferior and more of a liability than those from developed countries.</summary></entry></feed>